The greatest adventure of all is finding our place in the Circle of Life.
The Lion King is a family, animation, drama film directed by Roger Allers.
Young lion prince Simba, eager to one day become king of the Pride Lands, grows up under the watchful eye of his
father Mufasa; all the while his villainous uncle Scar conspires to take the throne for himself.
Amid betrayal and tragedy, Simba must confront his past and
find his rightful place in the Circle of Life.
Simba (voice), played by Matthew Broderick.
Nala (voice), played by Moira Kelly.
Timon (voice), played by Nathan Lane.
Pumbaa (voice), played by Ernie Sabella.
Mufasa (voice), played by James Earl Jones.
Scar (voice), played by Jeremy Irons.
The Lion King is a 1994 American animated musical drama film directed by Roger Allers and Rob Minkoff,
produced by Don Hahn, and written by Irene Mecchi, Jonathan Roberts, and Linda Woolverton.
It was produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and features an ensemble voice cast consisting of Matthew Broderick, James Earl Jones, Jeremy Irons,
Jonathan Taylor Thomas, Moira Kelly, Niketa Calame, Nathan Lane, Ernie Sabella, Whoopi Goldberg, Cheech Marin, Rowan Atkinson, and Robert Guillaume.
The story follows a young lion prince named Simba, who is exiled from his kingdom after
his father Mufasa is murdered by his uncle Scar to seize the throne.
As he grows up, Simba must decide whether to return home to
confront Scar and reclaim his place as king.
The Lion King was conceived during conversations among various Disney
executives, to whom several writers submitted early treatments.
Original director George Scribner had envisioned The Lion King as a nature documentary-style film, with Allers joining
as co-director after having worked in the story departments of several successful animated Disney films.
The Lion King's plot draws inspiration from several sources,
notably William Shakespeare's play Hamlet.
Woolverton, screenwriter for Disney's Beauty and the Beast (1991), drafted early versions of The Lion King's
script, which Mecchi and Roberts were hired to revise once Woolverton left to prioritize other projects.
Scribner departed due to disagreements over the studio's decision to reimagine the film as a musical, with
original songs by Elton John and Tim Rice, and Minkoff was hired to replace him in April 1992.
Throughout production, the creative team visited
Kenya for research and inspiration.
Released in theaters on June 24, 1994 by Walt Disney Pictures, The Lion King was
praised by critics for its music, story, themes, and animation.
With an initial worldwide gross of $763 million, it completed its theatrical run as the highest-grossing
film of 1994 and the second-highest-grossing film of all time, behind Jurassic Park (1993).
It held the title of highest-grossing animated film until
it was replaced by Finding Nemo in 2003.
The film remains the highest-grossing traditionally animated film of all time, as well as the
best-selling film on home video, having sold over 55 million copies worldwide.
However its initial gross remained the highest-grossing initial gross for a traditionally animated film until it
was surpassed 31 years later by Demon Slayer: Kimetsu no Yaiba – The Movie: Infinity Castle in 2025.
It won two Academy Awards, as well as the Golden Globe Award
for Best Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy.
It is considered by many to be among the greatest animated films ever made.
The success of the film launched a multibillion-dollar franchise comprising a Broadway adaptation, two direct-to-video follow-ups, two television series, and a
photorealistic remake (which itself spawned a prequel), which in 2019 also became the highest-grossing animated film at the time of its release.
In 2016, The Lion King was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of father murder, loss of
loved one, africa, lion, cartoon.
The tone is emotional.